Guide to the Graduate School of Education and Human Development records, 1930-1996 RG0011
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Graduate School of Education and Human Development records
1930-2011
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. Graduate School of Education and Human Development
RG0011
83 Linear Feet
Collection includes Reading Center client files, student papers, reports, newsletters, pamphlets, a time capsule, and a video tape, and range in date from 1930 to 1992. Materials were put on exhibit in the Fall of 2004 in the Gelman Library to celebrate the Centenary of the School.
Restrictions on Access
Series 1 is closed to research for 75 years from date of record creation.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through transfers from Graduate School of Education and Human Development.
Historical or Biographical Note
Clearly identified professional courses for teachers at The George Washington University were first offered in 1904-05, and the Division of Education, under the Columbian College, was established in 1907. In 1909 this division became the Teachers College, and in 1928 the School of Education.
By this time its faculty were staffing departments of education, educational psychology and home economics. In 1932, a year before it began its doctoral programs, the School accepted the responsibility for providing required physical education to all GW undergraduates, until the '60s when these requirements were dropped.
In 1977 the name was again changed to the School of Education and Human Development. The School is a unit within the University structure having jurisdiction over professional teacher education programs, as well as other professional programs in education and human development. Up until this time the School also oversaw the Reading Center.
In 1987 the School was organized into four departments: Department of Teacher Preparation and Special Education; the Department of Human Kinetics and Tourism; the Department of Educational Leadership, and the Department of Human Services. Each is headed by a department chair.
Since 1994 the School has been known as The Graduate School of Education and Human Development, when it transitioned from a comprehensive undergraduate/graduate entity to one focusing exclusively on graduate education. In 2004 the School celebrated its Centenary. The Dean of the School reports to the Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include Reading Center client files, student papers, reports, newsletters, pamphlets, a time capsule, and a video tape, and range in date from 1930 to 2011. Materials were put on exhibit in the Fall of 2004 in the Gelman Library to celebrate the Centenary of the School. They were transferred to the University Archives by the Dean of the Graduate School of Education and Human Development and faculty members. Note: Not all series are processed. Ask staff for assistance.
Collection Organization
Organized into nine series: Reading Center files; Student papers; Time capsule; Newsletter and pamphlets; Video tape; Adult education study; Report; Papers; and Centers and departmental files.
Education; Reports and studies; Reading; Special education; Washington (D.C.); George Washington University. School of Education and Human Development; George Washington University
- Reading Center files, ca.1970-ca.1990; RG0011 Series 1; 70.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of Reading Center client files [Reading Center closed in 1992]. They range in date from c.1970-c.1990. The material was transferred to University Archives in 1992.
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 1)
    General note
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 2)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 3)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 4)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 5)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 6)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 7)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 8)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 9)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 10)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 11)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 12)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 13)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 14)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 15)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 16)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 18)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 19)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 20)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 21)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 22)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 23)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 24)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 25)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 26)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 27)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 28)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 29)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 30)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 31)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 32)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 33)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 34)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 35)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 36)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 37)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 38)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 39)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 40)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 41)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 42)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 43)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 44)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 45)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 46)
  - Reading Center files, undated (Box 47)
- Student papers, 1934-1976; RG0011 Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of student papers - "The Practical Arithmetic for Seventh Grade" (1934), "Internal School Finances" (1953), "Inquiries into Selected Concepts Relating to Musicality in Children" (1964), and "Curriculum Materials, Educ. 207: Your Rights and Reponsibilities as an American Citizen"(1976). They range in date from 1934-76. The material was added to the University Archives collections from a backlog in 2003.
  - Student papers, undated (Box 1)
  - Student papers -- "The Practical Arithmetic for Seventh Grade" (1934), "Internal School Finances" (1953), "Inquiries into Selected Concepts Relating to Musicality in Children" (1964), and "Curriculum Materials, Educ. 207: Your Rights and Responsibilities as an American Citizen" (1976), 1934-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Time capsule, 1996; RG0011 Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of a time capsule of students ambitions after graduation, and is dated from 1996. The material was transferred to University Archives in 1996.
  - Time capsule, undated (Box 1)
  - Time capsule of students' ambitions after graduation, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Newsletters and pamphlets, 1993-2011; RG0011 Series 4; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of the newsletter "New Directions" and GSEHD program pamphlets. The material ranges in date from 1993 to 2011.
  - "Perspectives on Educational Certificate Programs", Margaret E. Holt and George J. Copos, eds., 1991; Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - GSEHD New Practitioners Program pamphlet, undated; Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - New Directions, 1993-1996, Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - New Directions, Fall 2008, Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - New Directions, Fall 2009, Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - New Directions, 2010 Spring -Fall; Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - New Directions, Spring 2011; Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - New Directions, Spring and Winter 2007 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - New Directions, Spring and Fall 2011 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - New Directions, Spring 2012 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - New Directions, 2001-2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - New Directions Mailer, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Adult education study, 1949; RG0011 Series 5; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of an "Adult Education Study" by James Fox, Ralph Ruffner, James Hall for the GW School of Education. It dates from 1949 and was donated to the University Archives by John Boswell in 2000.
  - Adult education study, undated (Box 1)
  - "Adult Education Study" by James Fox, Ralph Ruffner, James Hall (GW School of Education), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Videotape, 1988; RG0011 Series 6; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series consists of a videotape interview conducted by professor John Boswell, School of Education, with president Lloyd Elliott, on GW's role as an educational institution. It is dated from 1988 and was donated to the University Archives by John Boswell in 2001.
  - Videotape, undated (Box SHARED Box 20, Box 1)
  - Videotape interview conducted by Professor John Boswell, School of Education, with President Lloyd Elliott on GW's role as an educational institution, 1988 (Box SHARED Box 20, Box 1, Folder 1)
- Reports, 03/04/1974-2009; 1974-1985; RG0011 Series 7; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series consists of a report to the National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education, March 4-6, 1974 and March 26-28, 1984 (2 volumes), and the 2008-2009 Annual Report for the Granduate School of Education and Human Development.
  - Report to National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education, 03/4/1974-03/06/1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Report to the National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education, March 4-6, 1974 and March 26-28, 1984 (2 volumes), 03/26/1984-03/28/1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Papers, 1970-1992; RG0011 Series 8; 9 Linear feet
  This series consists of studies and papers on various aspects of education and training. The materials range in date from 1970-92. The material was transferred to University Archives in 1995.
  - Papers, undated (Box 1)
  - Gerson, Amy: Special Educator's Perceptions of Museum (2 copies)Service for Handicapped Individuals, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Razeghi, Jane Ann: A Descriptive Study of Data Included on Fairfax County Public Schools' Vocational Planning Guides During, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lewis, Kathi: A Examination of Autonomous Functioning of Learning Disabled Adolescents, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - McCaffrey, Mary: Professional Responsibilities and the Rights of Handicapped Children: The Development of a Training Curriculum for School Personnel, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Edwards, Norma Smith: An Investigation of the Relationship (2 copies)Between Reading Achievement and Short Term Auditory Retrieval and Storage in ESEA Title I Children from 12 DC Public Schools, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Wilson, Betty June: A Proposed Training Program for Special (2 copies) Education Training Aids in Virginia based upon Behavioral Objectives, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Papers, undated (Box 2)
  - McDonald, Phyllis: An Investigation of the Lowest Neaningful (2 copies) Score Concept and It's Relationship to Students with School Adjustment Problems, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Myers, Raymond Andrew: The Role of Self-Disclosure as Related to (2 copies) Selected Professional and Predictive Variables in a Graduate Humanistic Teacher Education Program, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Flynn, Nona Mitchell: The Effect of Positive Teacher Reinforcement and Classroom Social Structures on Class Behavior of Boys Diagnosed as Hyperactive for and During Medication, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bravi, Gerald D.: A Study of GWU Special Education Graduate (2 copies) Students' Perceptions, of Self and Others As Related to Success in Establishing an Effective Learning Milieu, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Eddy, William H.: Vocational Concept Formation by Educable (2 copies) Mental Retarded Students as a Function of Presentation Mode and Instructional Arrangement, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Riccio, L. Lawrence: Identification of Characteristics of Effective Citizen Advocates for the Handicapped and Citizen Advocacy Programs in the State of Virginia, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Papers, undated (Box 3)
  - Samango-Sprouse, Carol: A Comparative Study Analyzing the Behavioral Competencies of the Down Syndrome Neonate and the Normal Neonate Using the Brazelton Neonatal Behavioral Assessment Scale, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Perry, Howard L.: The Effect of Social Education Supporting Services and Teacher Attitudes toward Regular Class Integration of Midly Handicapped Children, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Goldman, Ester LaVine: Using the Wechsler Intelligence Scale for (2 copies) Children to Classify Intellectual Styles of Children with Learning Problems, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Tenorio, Sue Carol: Crisis Resource in Classroom Teacher's (2 copies) Perceptions of Problematic Students, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sapp, David Noel: Development, Status and Effects of the Prince Georges County Multiply Handicapped Work Study Programs, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Connolly, Margaret: Educators' Opinion Toward Factors Relative to the Location of Public School Special Education Program, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Howard, Harriet Cleiman: Physical Disability, Attitudes, and Equal Status Social Contact:The Young Adolescent, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Fearn, Kayte Marsh: A Descriptive Study of Models for Educational Diagnosis 1965-70, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Papers, undated (Box 4)
  - Jackson, Robert: The Effects of an Integrated Pre-School (2 copies) Setting on Handicapped and Non Handicapped Children: An Explorative and Comparative Study of Selected Behavioral Characteristics, Parent and Teacher Attitudes, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Schwartz, Gail Marie: An Evaluation Model for Special Education Service Delivery in State-Operated Adult And Juvenile Correctional Facilities, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Thomas, Marcia Ann: Observational Assessment of Stress-Related (2 copies) Behavior in Teacher Trainees: Development of an Instrument, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Barnes, Yvonne: Special Education Teacher Selection Procedures In the District of Columbia Public School System: A Descriptive Study, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Jordan, Renna Cramer: A Study of the Special Education Non-Categorical Preschool Class-Based Teachers Evaluation of the Peer Coaching Component of the Skillful Teacher Course, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Papers, undated (Box 5)
  - Moss, Margaret: Performance of Disadvantaged and Middle Class Preschool Children on a Language Test of Space and Location, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Hart, Donn Rae: Minor Physical Anomalies and Language and Behavior Variables in Selected 2 Year Olds, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Gill, Wanda Eileen: A Survey of the Gallaudet College School of Preparatory Studies Students and Teachers, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Durkos, Michael: A Survey of Nonstandard Diagnostic Techniques Reported by Public School Psychologists for the Assessment of Special Populations, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Lindo, Mamie Holloway: A History of Special Education in the District of Columbia Public Schools Prior to the Waddy Decree of August 1, 1972, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Hall, Donald Frank: The Educational Placement of Orthopedically Handicapped Children Served by the District of Columbia Society for Crippled Children, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Haigh, John Allen Jr.: A Study of the Inclusion of An Adaptive Behavior component In the Screening Procedure of Preschool Children In the District of Columbia, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Carter, Robert R.: Exceptionality Labels As A Biasing Factor In The Perceptions of Selected Regular Classroom Teachers in North Carolina, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Griggs, Sarah Lance: The Use of Selected Instruments in the Assessment of and Programming for Developmentally Retarded Pre-School Children, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Papers, undated (Box 6)
  - Platt, Judy Reiner: Right to an Education for Handicapped Children: A Study of Attorney General Opinions, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Flynn, Nona Mitchell: The Effect of Positive Teacher Reinforcement and Classroom Social Structures on Class Behavior of Boys Diagnosed as Hyperactive for and During Medication, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Howard, Harriet Cleiman: Physical Disability, Attitudes, and Equal Status Social Contact:The Young Adolescent, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Lawson, Marlene: The Relationship Between Ratings of Student Competencies as Defined by Methods Course Objectives and of Performance in Student Teaching in a Teacher Education Program, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Hall, Robert Edwin: A comparison of Characteristics of Sioux and Non-Sioux Teachers: Teacher Perceptions which Help Determine Educational Exceptionality in a Bisocial Setting, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Centers and departmental files, 1930-1991; RG0011 Series 9; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series contains memorandums, brochures, invitations, flyers, newsletters, posters, a bibliography, press releases, handbooks, programs, forms, and reports. They range in date from 1930 to 1991. This series consists of material relating to the Alumni Association for the Graduate School of Education and Human Development; the Reading Center; the Regional Rehabilitation Research Institution on Attitudinal, Legal and Leisure Barriers; rehabilitation counselor education; the Rehabilitation Research and Training Center; special education for early childhood; the graduate program in physical education for the handicapped; the Special Education Instructional Materials Center (SEIMC); the Department of Special Education; the complementary teacher program; degree descriptions; "Together... the Special Education/Early Child Program The George Washington University: a three year report"; the Physical Education Department; "Rx: Exchange: Therapeutic Recreation & Adaptive Physical Education; conferences; the Charles E. Smith Center; workshops; the Department of Physical Education, Health, and Recreation; the Women's Recreation Association, home economics, dietetics for navy nurses.
  - School of Education, 1938-2001 (Box 1)
  - Alumni - Alumni Association - School of Education Alumni Association, 1972-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Educational Exchange Programs, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Educational Opportunity Program, 1971-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Home Economics, 1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Physical Education Department, 02/1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Physical Education Department - Programs, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Physical Education for Men, 1967-07/26/1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Physical Education for Women, 1930-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Physical Education for Women - Annual Report to the President, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Reading Center 1977, 02/1978-01/10/1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Reading Center - Courses, 01/23/1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Regional Rehabilitation Research Institute on Attitudinal Legal and Leisure Barriers, 05/23/1977-04/1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Rehabilitation Counselor Education, 1970 ca. --10/13/1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rehabilitation Research and Training Center, 05/31/1966-06/15/1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - School of Education (1907-1977), 1938-1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - School of Education (1907-1977) - Admissions, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - School of Education - Courses, 1931-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - School of Education (1907-1977) - Faculty and Staff, 1943-1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - School of Education (1907-1977) - Graduate Programs, 1948-1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - School of Education (1907-1977) - History, 1903-1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - School of Education - History - Teacher's College, 1917 ca. --1941 ca. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - School of Education (1970-1977) - Project Head Start, 06/21/1965-06/30/1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - School of Education (1907-1977) - Reading Center, 1968-1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - School of Education (1907-1977) - Self-Evaluation of Teacher Education Programs, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - School of Education (1970-1977) - Symposia, Conferences, Institutes, Workshops, 1933-1983 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - School of Education (1907-1977) - Vocational Talent Exercises, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - School of Education and Human Development (1977), 1965-1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - School of Education and Human Development (1977) - Admissions, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - School of Education and Human Development (1977) - Center for Policy Studies, 10/1995 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - School of Education and Human Development (1977) - Center for Research and Services, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - School of Education and Human Development (1977) - Faculty, 06/1997 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - School of Education and Human Development (1977) - Graduate Programs, 1978-1995 ca. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - School of Education and Human Development - Graduate Programs - Annual Report, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - School of Education and Human Development - Graduate Programs - Doctoral Student Handbooks, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - School of Education and Human Development - Graduate Programs- Sponsored Project Awards and Activities, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - School of Education and Human Development (1977) - Museum Education, 1973-1985 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - School of Education and Human Development - Museum Education - Annual Reports, 1993-2001 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - School of Education and Human Development (1977) - Museum Education - Publications, 1978-1991 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - School of Education and Human Development (1977) - Off Campus Programs, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - School of Education and Human Development (1977) - Symposia, Conferences, Institutes, Workshops, 1963-1999 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - School of Education and Human Development (1977) - Undergraduate Programs, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Teacher Preparation and Special Education, 1968 ca. - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Teacher Preparation and Special Education - Early Childhood Program, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Printed materials, 2004-2011 (Box 1)
  - Faculty and Staff Directory, undated; Series 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Degree Program Materials, Undated; Series 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report, 2010-2011; Series 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Convocation Materials, 2004-2005; Series 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)